Guide to the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records, 1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated RL.00012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina records
1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina
RL.00012
217.5 Linear Feet approximately 135,000 items
North Carolina affiliate of the American Civil Liberties Union, founded in 1965 and based in Raleigh. The records of the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina (ACLU of N.C.) date from the 1960s to the mid-2000s. The collection is organized into the following series: ACLU Historical Files, Executive Director Files, Legal Program, Audiovisual Material, and Print Material. The files primarily focus on the investigation and prosecution of cases related to civil rights, public education relating to civil liberties, and lobbying for civil liberties and human rights. Materials include correspondence files from the Excecutive Director's office and other units in the ACLU of N.C., thousands of case files; administrative files on cases, operations, and attorney's activities; lobbying and subject files; and printed matter and other records relating to outreach and public education activities. There are also some a/v materials and electronic files. Topics include: the civil rights and legal status of legally under-represented groups such as juveniles and high school students, prisoners, gays, and immigrants; education and academic freedoms; religious freedom and separation of church and state; freedom of expression (including desecration of the flag); racial inequalities and injustices; reproductive rights; women's rights; police misconduct and the legality of search procedures; drug testing and the decriminalization of drugs; voting rights, including issues surrounding reapportionment; and workers' rights, including unionization. There are also files on the Ku Klux Klan, Confederate displays, and right-wing organizations. Many of these issues span decades of ACLU involvement. Researchers consulting case files and any other materials should be aware of privacy laws that govern the publication and use of these records. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
[Original recordings are closed to use. Use copies must be made for access. Electronic files have been mounted to a library server and need to be screened before use. Please contact Research Services for access to these materials before coming to use this collection.]
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1982 to 2009.
Historical Note
Since its inception in 1965, the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina (ACLU of NC) has investigated and prosecuted cases relating to civil liberties issues, especially free speech, prisoners' rights, religious freedoms, and reproductive freedom. The organization was founded in 1965 by two High Point, North Carolina area lawyers, James Mattocks and Charles Lambeth, as the North Carolina Civil Liberties Union (NCCLU), in response to the 1963 institution of the Speaker Ban Law by the NC State Legislature. The statute was repealed in winter of 1965. In 1969, the North Carolina Legal Foundation (NCLF) was formed to carry out the legal activities of the ACLU of NC By 1970, there were local offices in Charlotte, Greensboro, Greenville, and Raleigh, with Durham, Chapel Hill, and Asheville soon to follow. The NCCLU officially changed its name to the ACLU of NC in the 1970s, in response to a National office request. Originally its operations were based in Greensboro; in 1987 the office moved to its current location in Raleigh. The ACLU-NC and its Legal Foundation are governed by all-volunteer Boards of Directors, comprised of individuals from many different parts of the state and who work in a variety of professions. Most Board members are elected by the general membership to serve three-year terms and may serve no more than two consecutive terms. The Board sets the agenda for the organization and is charged with governance, oversight and securing the resources necessary for the organization to carry out its mission. The ACLU-NC and its legal arm maintain six permanent staff positions: Executive Director, Legal Director, Legislative Director, Racial Justice Fellow, Paralegal, and Office Manager. The staff also is supported by many interns, law clerks, and volunteers.
Chronology List (dates are approximate in some cases)
1960s Jim Shields acted as ACLU liaison to North Carolina
1965 Founding of the North Carolina Civil Liberties Union, later renamed ACLU of NC
1960s-1970 Norman Smith, Executive Director
1970-1989/1990 George Gardner, Executive Director
1989/1990-1994 Jim Shields, Executive Director
1994-2002 Deborah Ross, Executive Director and Legal Director
Jan. 2003-Nov. 2003 Patricia Camp, Executive Director
Nov. 2003-May 2004 Renee Hill, Interim Executive Director
May 2004- Jennifer Rudinger, Executive Director
Collection Overview
The records of the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina (ACLU of NC) span forty years, from its inception in the early 1960s to its activities in the mid-2000s. The files provide documentation on nearly all aspects of the organization's operations, primarily focusing on the investigation of cases related to civil rights and many related issues, the legal prosecution of cases, public education relating to civil liberties, and lobbying for civil liberties and human rights. Materials include correspondence files from the Excecutive Director's office and other units in the ACLU of NC, beginning from the earliest years; thousands of case files dating from 1969 through the mid-2000s; the legal assistant's files on cases, operations, and attorney's activities; lobbying and subject files; and printed matter and other records relating to the ACLU-NC's outreach and public education activities. There are also some slides related to arts cases, videocassette and audiocassette recordings, and electronic files. Commonly recurring social and legal issues to which the ACLU of NC dedicated its efforts and resources include but are not limited to: the civil rights and legal status of legally under-represented groups such as juveniles and high school students, prisoners, gays, and immigrants; education and academic freedoms; religious freedom and separation of church and state; freedom of expression (including desecration of the flag); racial inequalities and injustices; reproductive rights; women's rights; police misconduct and the legality of search procedures; drug testing and the decriminalization of drugs; voting rights, including issues surrounding reapportionment; and workers' rights, including unionization. There are also many files on the Ku Klux Klan, Confederate displays, and right-wing organizations in NC
The collection is open to use. However, researchers consulting case files and any other materials in this collection should be aware of privacy laws that govern the publication and use of these records, especially in the case of third party information. Most personal names have been removed from case file titles in this web-accessible collection guide. The full version is available only to on-site researchers.
The Legal Program Series, the largest series in the collection at 260 boxes, chiefly consists of court case and other investigations files, and were created and maintained by the branch of the ACLU of NC called the North Carolina Legal Foundation. The files were marked variously as coming from the Office of the Legal Counsel or the Legal Program. These files were kept in their original order, which was generally chronological, though there are many overlapping series and fragmented sequences, some of which are alphabetical. When possible, the nature of the case or investigation is noted in a few words for each entry; keyword searching is the best means to discover names or topics (e.g., parental consent, prayer, 1st Amendment, employee, free speech, etc.).
Files in the Executive Director Office Series (90 boxes) refer to meetings, annual ACLU national conferences, litigation and political action strategizing, fundraising, and membership, and contain many individual legislative and court case files maintained by the Executive Director's Office (who at times in the ACLU of NC's history also served as the Legal Director). Extensive research and "issues" files, as they were often called, found both in the Legal Program and Executive Office Series, were most often used to support the case and investigative work, and therefore cover topics similar to the case files. Other subject files reflect the Executive Director's efforts to learn about issues relating to other affiliates of the ACLU.
Smaller but significant components of the collection include the Audiovisual Material Series, housing videocassettes and audio recordings, and the Print Material Series, which houses publications, clippings, reports, and other print material created by the ACLU of NC as well as material from other organizations. A nearly complete run of the ACLU of NC's newsletter, Liberty, can be found here, as well as multiple issues from such publications as Prison Law Monitor, Veteran's Advocate, and Youth Law News. Other publications are filed by topic. Many press releases, clippings, and files related to media relations are found in the Executive Director Office Series, and to a lesser extent in the Legal Program Series.
Researchers interested in the earliest history of the ACLU of NC should consult the small Historical Files Series which contains a 1970 history of the organization written by Daniel Pollitt and George Scheer, as well as copies of the original founding documents of incorporation, board and legal foundation meeting minutes from the 1960s to the 1980s, and other files. More complete files of early correspondence, meetings, and legal cases dating from the 1960s and 1970s can be found in other series.
Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
The records of the ACLU of NC are arranged into the following series: ACLU Historical Files, Executive Director Files, Legal Program, Audiovisual Material, and Print Material. The Executive Director Series is roughly organized chronologically by decade, and thus relates to individual directors (also called Executive Secretary in the early years) who assembled the sets of files, including the earliest and most current directors. The Legal Program Series is further subdivided into Case Files, also chronologically organized, and by far the largest group of files in the collection; Legal Director Files; and Legal Committee. All of these series and their divisions are described in full detail in this collection guide. Financial, medical, and personnel records were removed prior to the transfer of the collection but there may still be similar files present whose contents are protected by privacy laws.
Videocassettes; Machine-readable records; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; Voting -- North Carolina; Searches and seizures -- Laws and legislation -- North Carolina; Reproductive rights -- North Carolina; Racial profiling in law enforcement; Freedom of speech -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Slides (photographs); Police misconduct -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Laws, etc.; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Racism -- Political aspects -- United States; Prisoners -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; Race discrimination -- Law and legislation -- North Carolina; Educational law and legislation -- United States; Elections -- North Carolina; Employee rights -- North Carolina; Freedom of religion -- North Carolina; Church and state -- North Carolina; Civil rights -- North Carolina -- History; Drug legalization -- North Carolina; Drug testing -- Laws and legislation -- North Carolina; Gay rights -- North Carolina; Academic freedom; African Americans -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; Audiocassettes; Children -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; Juvenile justice, Administration of -- North Carolina; Immmigrants -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; Human Rights -- North Carolina -- History; Gays -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; American Civil Liberties Union -- History; American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina -- History; Ku Klux Klan (1915- ) -- North Carolina; United States. Constitution. 1st Amendment; United States. Constitution. 4th Amendment; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- ACLU of NC Historical Files Series, 1969-1984 and undated, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Smallest series includes photocopies of original incorporation papers, by-laws, a history of the NCCLU written by Daniel Pollitt and George Scheer in 1970, and other documents relating to the organization's earliest years of formation, when it was known as the NCCLU. Filed in the front of the folder is a list of Executive Directors with term years, and other key individuals in the organization. Additional early records from the 1960s and 1970s can be found in the other main series.
  - Historical files (Box 1-1A)
- Executive Director Office Series, 1965-2001 and undated, 90 boxes
  Arranged in the following groupings: chronological subseries by decade relating to Executive Directors in office during that period, beginning with the 1970s; followed by the Board of Trustees Subseries; and last, the Publicity and Media Subseries. The original chronological groupings, some arranged internally in alphabetical order, were maintained by Executive Office staff and chiefly consisted of administrative files, correspondence files, requests for legal assistance (including rejections), and subject folders used for personal research and development, or in direct support of accepted cases. The presence of case files is explained partly by the fact that for some time the Executive Director functioned simultaneously as the Legal Director; later on, these two positions were again separate administrative functions, after which most of the case files were maintained by the Office of Legal Counsel, or the Legal Program, as it became known. See also the Legal Program Series for related case files.
  Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
  - 1960s-1970s Files Subseries
    Contents represent the activities of the ACLU of NC during its earliest years. For other early files concerning the foundation of what was then termed the NCCLU, see the ACLU Historical Files Series.
    - 1966-1968 Files
      Primarily the correspondence files of Rosemary Yardley and Jane S. Patterson, who served successively as executive office assistant. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU index of materials (Box 2)
      - ACLU News Release, 1968 July 30 (Box 2)
      - Atkins v. City of Charlotte (Box 2)
      - Attacks on ACLU and NCCLU (Box 2)
      - Biennial Conference Reports (Box 2)
      - Board of Directors, etc. (Box 2)
      - Bumper, Wayne Darnell, case (Box 2)
      - Cases involved in (Box 2)
      - Cases involved in other than prisoners (Box 2)
      - Cases to investigate (Box 2)
      - Charlotte dinner (Box 2)
      - Citizens Against Legalized Murder (Box 2)
      - Civil disobedience discussion (Box 2)
      - Collins v. Alexander County Board of Education (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, general (Box 2)
      - Correspondence from affiliate agencies (Box 2)
      - Correspondence from ACLU until 1968 Jan. (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to ACLU until 1968 Jan. (Box 2)
      - Correspondence to members (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with membership and public (Box 3)
      - Councils on Human Relations, the Association of (Box 3)
      - Director addresses, commuter sheets (Box 3)
      - Early loose correspondence, legal case information on religion in schools, 1969 Nov. (Box 3)
      - Expenses (Box 3)
      - Financial records (Box 3)
      - Financial reports from National (Box 3)
      - General business [finances] (Box 3)
      - Greenville, E.C.U. case (Box 3)
      - Ideas from affiliates (Box 3)
      - Legislative Committee, State and National (Box 3)
      - Legislative proposals (Box 3)
      - Loose correspondence, Gardner, 1969 (Box 3)
      - March meeting of membership (Box 3)
      - Membership by area (Box 3)
      - Membership drive, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Membership mailing, 1968 Jan.-Mar. (Box 3)
      - Membership mailing, 1968 Mar., 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Newsletter, 1966-1967 (correspondence and 2 photos) (Box 3)
      - Newsletters from affiliates, Sen. Ervin (Box 3)
      - Newspaper clippings, civil liberties, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - 1969 Nominating Committee, Board of Directors (Box 3)
      - Position papers from ACLU (Box 3)
      - Press notices, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
      - Prisoner mail: refusal, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Prison system: jail system (Box 4)
      - Prisoner's letter forms (Box 4)
      - Request letters from individuals concerned: prisoner refusal (Box 4)
      - Selective Service Law Institute (Box 4)
      - UNC speaker ban case (Box 4)
      - Williams, Rev. Frank, case (Box 4)
    - 1969-1970 Files
      Primarily the correspondence and subject files of Norman B. Smith as Executive Secretary (i.e. Director) and General Counsel and of Kate Erwin as Executive Secretary. Arranged in some rough alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU pamphlets, leaflets (Box 4)
      - Affiliate Board minutes (Box 4)
      - Annual Meeting, 1970 (Box 4)
      - By-laws (Box 4)
      - Chapters:
        - Boone (Box 4)
        - Chapel Hill (Box 4)
        - Charlotte (Box 4)
        - Durham (Box 4)
        - Greensboro (Box 4)
        - Greenville (Box 4)
        - Raleigh (Box 4)
      - Dove, Mark (Box 4)
      - Elon College newspaper (Box 4)
      - Graham Award (Box 4)
      - Inside ACLU newsletters, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
      - Legal pamphlet, Know Your Rights (correspondence about) (Box 5)
      - Legislative recommendations (Box 5)
      - Membership (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence files, folders 1-9 of 14 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence files, folders 10-14 of 14 (Box 6)
      - ACLU Files (National Office)
        Set of files kept by the NCCLU, arranged in alphabetical order. Includes subject files, committee minutes and working papers, and memos to affiliates. This is followed by ACLU of NC Executive Office subject files in random order as received.
        - Academic Freedom Committee minutes and working papers, 1969 (Box 6)
        - Art and Communication Division, minutes and working papers, 1969 (Box 6)
        - Board minutes and working papers, 1969 (Box 6)
        - Church-State Committee minutes and working papers (Box 6)
        - Communication Committee minutes and working papers (Box 6)
        - Due Process Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
        - Equality Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
        - Free Speech/Association Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
        - Labor Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
        - Memos to affiliates (Box 7)
        - Planning and Steering Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
        - Press Releases Board statements and legislative testimonies (Box 7)
        - Privacy Committee minutes and working papers (Box 7)
      - ACLU of NC Executive Office subject files:
        - Royal, David (Box 7)
        - Voter residency requirements (Blumstein b. Ellington) (Box 7)
        - Winston-Salem Obscenity Ordinance (Box 7)
        - Freedom of belief/expression/association (Box 7)
        - Censorship/obscenity-books, newspapers, Post Office, Customs Bureau (Box 7)
        - Motion pictures and plays (Box 7)
        - Radio and TV (Box 7)
        - Academic freedom (Box 7)
        - Education/scholarship denials (Box 7)
        - Religion/church-state/education (Box 7)
        - Public issues (religion/church-state), birth control, etc. (Box 7)
        - Religious conscience (oaths, religious conscientious objection) (Box 7)
        - Freedom of speech/association (passports-visas-citizens) (Box 7A)
        - Congressional investigation committees (Box 7A)
        - Internal security measures (i.e. loyalty oaths, communism) (Box 7A)
        - The vote: elections/ballots (including reapportionments, etc.) (Box 7A)
        - Right of assembly (including demonstrations) (Box 7A)
        - Labor/employment (also internal union democracy) (Box 7A)
        - Miscellaneous: freedom of belief/expression/association (Box 7A)
        - Conscientious objection to particular wars (and drafts) (Box 7A)
        - Equality before the law (race relations and minorities) (Box 7A)
        - Education (Box 7A)
        - Employment (Box 7A)
        - Housing (Box 7A)
        - Voting rights (Box 7A)
        - Private organizational discrimination (Box 7A)
        - American Indians (Box 7A)
        - Court proceedings: discrimination against Negroes, indigents and minorities (Box 7A)
        - Welfare recipients: indigents, poor (Box 7A)
        - Rights of mentally ill (Box 7A)
        - Military justice (Box 8)
        - Legislative investing committees (Box 8)
        - Executive branch administration (Box 8)
        - Court proceedings (Box 8)
        - Police practices: wiretapping (Box 8)
        - All other illegal police practices (Box 8)
        - Roger Baldwin Foundation (Box 8)
      - Administrative Executive Office Files, 1960s-1970s:
        - Meeting and celebrations (Box 8)
        - Outside organizations and publications (Box 9)
        - Affiliate publications (Box 9)
        - Press releases (Box 9)
        - Monthly publications (Box 9)
        - Pamphlets, leaflets, statements, etc. (Box 9)
        - Biennial conference (substantive) (Box 9)
        - Funds, grants, bequests (Box 9)
        - NCCLU Foundation, Inc. (Box 9)
        - Affiliate, Board of Directors: general correspondence (Box 9)
        - Affiliate, Board minutes (Box 9)
        - Mailings to boards (Box 9)
        - Mailings to 1970 board (Box 9)
        - Board resignations (Box 9)
        - Affiliate board committees (Box 9)
        - Affiliate chapters (Box 9)
        - Potential affiliate chapters (Box 9)
        - Executive trips to National Office (Box 9)
        - Policy Manual of ACLU (Box 9)
        - Affiliate office materials (Box 9)
        - Conferences and chapter celebrations (Box 9)
        - Biennial Conference arrangements (non-substantive) (Box 9)
        - Organizational/educational/informational matters (Box 9)
        - Membership Department: general (Box 10)
        - Comments by members or others (Box 10)
        - Contributions, resignations (Box 10)
        - Public Relations Department: general (Box 10)
        - Requests for speakers (yes) (Box 10)
        - Attacks and commendations (Box 10)
        - Monthly publications (Box 10)
        - Office administration: general (Box 10)
        - Personnel employment application (Box 10)
        - Volunteers (Box 10)